Vinav Alsa

Atlanta, United States|+1 (334) 440-1067|alsavinay@outlook.com

| LinkedIn | GitHub | Trailblazer | |

PROFECITINAL SUMMARY

A professional with overall 4+ years of experience in Salesforce as a Developer. which includes Salesforce CRM, Configuration, Development, Deployment, and system design, and managing Reports, Dashboards for Business Analysis, and advanced features like the Lightning platform.

TECHNICAL SKILLS:

- Salesforce Administration: Custom and standard objects, fields, page layouts, record types, validation rules, schema builder, flow Builder, Process Builder, workflow rules, approval process, permission sets, Org, and object level security, OWD, Data Management.
- Salesforce Development: Apex programming language, Asynchronous and Synchronous Apex, Batch Apex, Triggers, SOQL, SOSL, triggers, DML, Visualforce, Lightning Web Components Framework, Integration, REST API, SOAP API.
- Salesforce Clouds: Sales Cloud, Service Cloud, Community Cloud.
- Programming Languages and Database: C++, Python, MySQL, SQLite
- Web Development: HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Bootstrap, GitHub.
- Tools and software: Agile Methodology, Software Development Lifecycle, Jira, Microsoft Visual Studio, Deployment tools.
- Soft Skills: Leadership, Communication, Time management, Teamwork, Problem-solving, Work ethic, Creativity.

CERTIFICATIONS

Salesforce certified Platform Developer I | Salesforce Certified Administrator

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE:

Salesforce Developer at Cognizant Technology Services, Hyderabad, India.

August 2021 - June 2023

- Implemented multiple integration **APIs** to retrieve data from external sources, provided **live service support**, particularly in the insurance industry project (DLG-Direct line group), And used Tools like **Jira**, **GitHub**, and **Visual Studio code**.
- Responsible for implementing component-based security by configuring user permissions, record type permissions, and field-level security
 within the Salesforce org, Debugging and troubleshooting issues raised by users, and ensuring the smooth functioning of the Salesforce
 applications.
- Involved in customizing various aspects of the Salesforce platform, including **custom objects**, **fields**, **record types**, **forms**, **layouts**, **custom tabs**, and **applications**, as well as maintaining **workflow rules**, **approvals**, and **relationships** between **objects**.
- Worked on Data Loader To perform CURD Operation and Implemented various advanced fields like Picklist Fields, Master-Detail Fields,
 Custom Formula Fields, and defined Field Dependencies for custom Picklist fields.
- Understanding and analyzing business requirements, mapping them to Salesforce functionality, and implementing applications using Agile Scrum
 Methodology with change-sets for sandbox-to-sandbox deployments; collaborating with stakeholders to translate requirements into technical
 specifications for role-based access controls, permission sets, queues, and data security measures; modifying configurations like page layouts
 and triggers to streamline case management processes, deploying changes via user stories across sprints after thorough testing and UAT.
- Developed custom **Apex classes, triggers,** and **flows** to extend the functionality of Salesforce which included the enhancement of registration request functionality for a customer portal, effectively addressing data inconsistencies and slashing ticket counts from 50-60 per month to a mere 5-6 over a month-long period.
- Developed a user-friendly digital UI web-based signup form for onboarding new regions, seamlessly **integrating LWC Framework** with **Apex** and **triggers**. Ensured robust communication between systems through **REST and SOAP APIs**, deploying the new functionality within the existing platform framework.

SFDC developer & Admin at LTIMindtree Ltd, Hyderabad, India.

Sep 2018 - Oct 2021

- Developed **Apex classes, triggers, Visualforce pages, components,** and controller extensions to create custom functionality and user interfaces within the Salesforce platform, including public-facing websites using **Force.com** Sites.
- Set up Marketing Campaigns, Campaign Hierarchies, Lead Queries, Assignment rules, **Web-to-Lead** and **Auto-Response rules**, Configured Campaign Management, **Campaign Influence**, and **Lead Conversion**.
- Maintaining Workflow rules and Approvals, creating relationships between the objects.
- Managed user accounts, roles, profiles, and sharing rules to define access levels, and permissions, implemented data management processes, including data migration using the Data Loader tool, and configured security settings like tab permissions, record type permissions, field-level security, and sharing rules to control access and data visibility.
- Involved In customization, Creating custom labels and Custom settings, custom buttons, and Customizing fields, record types, forms and layouts, custom tabs, and applications.
- Used Visualforce Templates and Placeholders to encapsulate **page elements** to be reused across several Visualforce pages, **Tab permissions**, **Record Type permissions**, and **Field Level Security** to implement **Component-based security**.
- Implemented Data migration using Data Loader, Creating/adding, and managing Users, Roles, and Profiles, and setting up sharing rules.
- Involved in **Salesforce.com** Application Setup activities and customized the apps to match the functional needs of the organization Worked with standard Salesforce objects like **Accounts, Contacts, Leads, Cases,** and **Opportunities**
- Created Custom Visualforce components and attributes to override the look and feel of standard Visualforce components.

EDUCATION:

Auburn University at Montgomery, MS, Computer Engineering, Montgomery, AL, United States.

January 2023 - December 2024

Coursework – Could computing and Advanced Data Structures, Algorithms, Object Oriented Design, Introduction to Database Management Systems.

Jawaharlal Nehru Technological University, B-Tech, Hyderabad, India.

August 2018 - June 2021